Guide to the Justus Forward Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Justus Forward papers
1752-1813
MS 219
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
(6 boxes)
The papers consist primarily of sermons preached by Justus Forward between 1754 and 1813. Also included are correspondence, largely on church matters, other church papers, a notebook kept by Forward while at Yale College (1752-1753), and nine diaries (1759-1814) mostly with brief entries. There is one description of the military developments in the French-Indian War for the month of July, 1759. Of particular interest in the correspondence is an exchange with Dr. Martin Phelps, later excommunicated from the church, on the question of communion.
Forward, Justus, 1730-1814
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Earl M. Ingham and Norman W. Ingham in 1966 and 1978. Gift of Norman W. Ingham, 1993.
Scope and Contents
The Justus Forward Papers contain correspondence, diaries, over one thousand sermons, church papers, Forward's Yale papers, one hardback book, fragments of two Congressional bills, and miscellaneous materials. The period covered is from 1752 to 1814.
Correspondence includes letters of church business, as well as debates and discussions of Reverend Forward and colleagues on religious subjects and foreign policy. Of particular interest is an exchange with Dr. Martin Phelps, later excommunicated from the church, on the question of communion.
Biographical / Historical
Justus Forward graduated from Yale College in 1754. He studied theology with Rev. Timothy Woodbridge and was licensed to preach by the Hampshire Association of Ministers in 1755. Forward was pastor of the Congregational Church in Belchertown, Massachusetts, from 1756-1812.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Congregational churches -- Massachusetts; Belchertown (Mass.) -- Religion; Massachusetts; New England; United States -- History -- French and Indian War, 1754-1763; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Diaries; Sermons; Clergy; Forward, Justus, 1730-1814; Phelps, Martin, 1757-1838; Taggart, Samuel, 1754-1825; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1754; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory, 1752-1814
  - Correspondence, arranged chronologically, 1773-1812
    - Wood, David (Somers, Mass.), 1773 July 30 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 1)
      General
      Letter asking Forward to assist in ordination of infamous Samuel Ely.
    - Taylor, John (Belchertown, Mass.), 1790 November 23 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 2)
      Letter advises Forward not to move into the new church before the building has been formally presented to the town.
    - Forward, Justus (Belchertown, Mass.), 1790 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 3)
      Reply to Mr. Taylor with reasons for his actions regarding the new church.
    - Society, Congregational Charitable (Boston, Mass.), 1803 January (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 4)
      Letter (with enclosed subscription paper) notifying Forward of the formation of a government-sponsored corporation to collect, manage, and dispose of funds for the relief of widows and orphans of deceased ministers.
    - Scott, Amasa (Shirley, Mass.), 1803 February 7 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 5)
      Social correspondence.
    - Field, Lemuel (Belchertown, Mass.), 1804 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 6)
      Part of correspondence that has explored several religious problems. In this particular letter, Field argues against infant baptism.
    - Scott, Amasa (Peachem, Vt.), 1804 April 30 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 7)
    - Taggart, Samuel (Washington, D.C.)
      Samuel Taggart (1754-1825) was a graduate of Dartmouth College who served as pastor of a church in Colrain, Mass. He was elected as a Federalist to the Eighth Congress and to six succeeding Congresses. He continued as pastor until Oct. 28, 1818. He died in Colrain April 25, 1825.
      - 1808 February 9 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 8)
        This letter is concerned with Taggart's disenchantment with the nation's foreign policy, which he claims is influenced by powerful voices in Paris. He complains about the effects of the Embargo Act on American merchants and discusses the propriety of the British in regard to the Chesapeake incident and exaggerated charges of British impressment of American sailors.
      - 1808 March 21 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 9)
        In this letter Taggart expresses his fears that the President is leading the nation toward a needless war with Great Britain. Taggart suspects clandestine dealings between Washington and Paris.
    - Hawley, Timothy (Morgan), 1808 November 14 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 10)
      Forward's cousin here relates circumstances surrounding his life in new settlement of New Connecticutt.
    - Parish, Amelia (Reading), 1812 June 17 (Box 1, Folder 1, Item 11)
      Letter revealing interest to live in Belchertown and to devote life in God's service.
    - Correspondence between Reverend Forward and Dr. Martin Phelps (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Martin Phelps (1757-1838) was a graduate of Yale College, Class of 1776. After serving as physician and deacon in the Congregational Church in Haverhill, New Hampshire, he went to Belchertown. In 1796 his failure to join the village church provoked notice. He was finally called on by the minister (Forward) and the deacons for his reasons. The two parties rushed into print and the letters between Phelps and Forward were published. By the desire of the Reverend Aaron Bascom, the pastor of the church in Chester, Phelps removed thither. Soon a bitter controversy developed involving the entire community and Dr. Phelps was excommunicated from the church. In 1807 he was chosen as an Anti-Federalist to represent the town in the state legislature. He subsequently renounced infant baptism and was admitted to the nearest Baptist church in Hinsdale. He was instrumental in starting a Baptist society in Chester. He died there on Nov. 26, 1838. This particular correspondence consists of four letters from Phelps to Forward and a copy of Forward's preface and his remarks to the public. The letters are concerned with Phelps' arguments behind his refusal to join the church. The basic problem involves his interpretation of the qualities necessary for communion. Phelps claims that the church's practice is in opposition to the church's covenant. There has been no test to see if those receiving communion actually possess the essential characteristics of real Christians. Besides presenting his own arguments, Phelps refutes his opponent's reasons for church practice.
  - Journals (nine diaries) (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    These journals contain little more than a daily account of the weather, deaths, and visits to friends. There is one description of the military developments in the French-Indian War for the month of July, 1759. In the diary for 1812 Forward mentions Bonaparte's march on Europe.
    - No. 8, 1759 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 1)
    - No. 27, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 2)
    - No. 41, 1794 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 3)
    - No. 42, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 4)
    - No. 43, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 5)
    - No. 49, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 6)
    - No. 52, 1805 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 7)
    - No. 59, 1812 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 8)
    - No. 61, 1814 (Box 1, Folder 3, Item 9)
  - Yale papers
    - Student notebook, Yale College, 1752-1753. (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 1)
      Arguments for theological debate with a list of debate topics. Questions range from legality of slavery to immortality of animals.
    - "Origin of Royal Courtship. A poem on the courtship and marriage of the patriarch Isaac. Interspersed with moral reflections. Written in 1757 by a gentle man educated at Yale Colledge." (Box 1, Folder 4, Item 2)
  - Church material
    - Papers relating to the case of Stephen Fairfield vs. Nathan Parsons and the church council of 1774 concerning it. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Case is a suit involving failure on the part of Parsons to abide by a verbal contract he supposedly made before witnesses.
    - List of church members in Belchertown in 1793. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Papers regarding a church council in Belchertown, 1797 Nov (Box 1, Folder 7)
      This council was called to decide whether Forward and his church had acted criminally, causing the withdrawal from communion of a certain faction of the church. This controversy was an outgrowth of the Forward-Phelps debate.
    - "An Attempt briefly to Explain the Epistle to the Romans..." (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Sermons (incomplete number series, Nos. 17-2289)
    - 1755, 1757-1761 (Box 1, Folder 9-12)
    - 1762-1770 May (Box 2)
    - 1770 June-1778 (Box 3)
    - 1780-1804 September (Box 4)
    - 1804 October-1813, undated (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous papers
    - "With Regard to the Article of Falsifying Charges agt. me by Capt. Nath. Dwight..." (1758) (Box 6)
      3 sheets. Forward's answer to charges of refusing to quarter a company of Dwight's men in his house.
    - "An Allegory. Faintly shewing, the analogy of Literals, and Spirituals; Temporals and Eternals; Externals; and Enternals," by Lemuel Field, 1801. (Box 6)
      Dedicated to Rev. Justus Forward.
    - Two bills
      - Printed copy of "Bill for Incorporating the Society for Relieving Widows and Orphans of the Ministers of the Congregational churches in the Province of Massachusetts-Bay," provincial legislature, 1767 (Box 6)
        Inscribed, "Belchertown."
      - Fragment of printed bills: "In provincial Congress, Cambridge, December 6, 1774" (Box 6)
        Calling on parishes of province to give aid to inhabitants of Boston suffering from results of Boston Port Bill. Inscribed on reverse: "For the Revd. Mr. J. Forward, Belcher Town."
    - Miscellaneous papers, mostly sermons. Advisory hints to children. Proposal to print a volume of sermons of Justus Forward, A.M.
      - "Dedication Anthem" -- "The Lord reigneth.. ." (Box 6)
        Text not in JF's handwriting.
      - "Friendly Advice to youth in the following Aphorisms" (Box 6)
        One sheet folded into four pages.
      - Notes on political philosophy (perhaps extracts from JF's reading) (Box 6)
        Made on back and margin of a report of choice of electors at the Belchertown town meeting of 1812 Nov 12.
    - Book-- The Religion of Nature Delineated, by Mr. Wollaston, 7th ed. (London, 1750). (Box 6)
      Inside front cover is Forward's book-plate; on fly-leaf inscription: "Justus Forward's book, July 5th Anno Domini 1753 Price 15/6 y M)."